Pat Mitchell: You have brought us images from the Yemen Times.
بات ميتشيل : لقد جلبت لنا صوراً من صحيفة " اليمن تايمز "
And take us through those,
وقد استخدمتيها
and introduce us to another Yemen.
لكي تعبري لنا عن زاوية جديدة من اليمن
Nadia Al-Sakkaf: Well, I'm glad to be here.
نادية السقاف : في الحقيقة انا ممتنة جداً لكوني هنا
And I would like to share with you all
واريد ان اشارككم جميعاً
some of the pictures that are happening today in Yemen.
بصور عن بعض الامور التي تحدث اليوم في اليمن
This picture shows a revolution
هذه الصورة تظهر جانباً من جوانب الثورة
started by women,
والتي بدأت بنسوة
and it shows women and men
وهي تظهر النساء والرجال سوية
leading a mixed protest.
يقودون ثورة مختلطة
The other picture
وهذه الصورة الاخرى
is the popularity of the real need for change.
انها تعبر عن احتياج الشعب للتغيير
So many people are there.
والعديد من الاشخاص هناك
The intensity of the upspring.
يقومون اليوم ويعبرون عن آرائهم
This picture shows that the revolution
هذه الصورة تظهر ان الثورة
has allowed opportunities for training,
فتحت ابواب جديدة للتدريب
for education.
والتعليم
These women are learning about first aid
هؤلاء النسوة هنا يتدربن على الاسعافات الاولية
and their rights according to the constitution.
ويتعلمن عن حقوقهم الدستورية.
I love this picture.
انا احب هذه الصورة
I just wanted to show
انا اريد فقط ان اريكم
that over 60 percent of the Yemeni population
انه اكثر من 60% من شعب اليمن
are 15 years and below.
عمره أقل من الخامسة عشر
And they were excluded from decision-making,
وقد كان كل هؤلاء معزولون عن صناعة القرار
and now they are in the forefront of the news,
ولكنهم اليوم في صدارة نشرات الاخبار
raising the flag.
يرفعون أعلامهم
English --
هذه اللغة الانجليزية
you will see, this is jeans
كما ترون .. هذا بنطال من الجينز
and tights,
مُخصر قليلاً
and an English expression --
وهذا التعبير باللغة الانجليزية
the ability to share with the world
من اجل ان يسمع العالم أصوات الثوار
what is going on in our own country.
ويعلمون ما يجري في بلدهم
And expression also,
وانواع التعبير تلك
it has brought talents.
توسع نطاق المهارات
Yemenis are using cartoons
اليوم اليمنيون يستخدمون الرسوم الكرتونية
and art,
والفنون
paintings, comics,
والرسم والتلوين والقصص القصيرة
to tell the world and each other
من اجل ان يخبروا العالم .. ومن حولهم
about what's going on.
عما يجري على الساحة في اليمن اليوم
Obviously, there's always the dark side of it.
وحتماً .. هناك جانب ممقت من تلك الصور
And this is just one of the less-gruesome pictures
هذه بعض من الصور الاقل شناعة
of the revolution
عن الثورة
and the cost that we have to pay.
انه الثمن الذي يجب ان ندفعه من اجل تقدمنا
The solidarity
ان التضامن
of millions of Yemenis across the country
الذي اعترى ملايين اليمنين عبر البلاد
just demanding the one thing.
لا يطالب الا بشيء واحد هو التغيير
And finally, lots of people are saying
و بشكل متزايد هناك العديد ممن يقولون
that Yemen's revolution
ان الثورة اليمنية
is going to break the country.
سوف تقود البلد الى الانقسام
Is it going to be so many different countries?
هل ستغدو اليمن عدة دويلات ؟
Is it going to be another Somalia?
هل ستغدو مثل الصومال ؟
But we want to tell the world that, no,
نحن الشعب اليمني نريد ان نقول للعالم .. لا لن يحدث هذا
under the one flag, we'll still remain as Yemeni people.
فنحن جميعاً ننطوي أسفل العلم اليمني .. نحن لم نتغير نحن في النهاية يمنيون
PM: Thank you for those images, Nadia.
بات ميتشيل : شكرأً نادية على هذه الصور
And they do, in many ways,
وهذه بصورة ما تعبر
tell a different story
عن زوايا جديدة
than the story of Yemen,
من قصة اليمن التي نعرفها
the one that is often in the news.
والتي عادة ما تتناقلها قنوات الاخبار
And yet, you yourself
وأنت .. أيضاً
defy all those characterizations.
تقوضين كل تلك الصور المسبقة الصنع عن اليمن
So let's talk about the personal story for a moment.
دعينا نتحدث عن حياتك الشخصية الآن
Your father is murdered.
لقد تم اغتيال والدك
The Yemen Times already has
وصحيفة " اليمن تايمز " لديها سمعة
a strong reputation in Yemen
قوية في اليمين
as an independent English language newspaper.
على انها صحيفة مستقلة ناطقة باللغة الانجليزية
How did you then
فكيف استطعت
make the decision and assume the responsibilities
ان تمسكي بزمام الامور وتتولي المسؤوليات
of running a newspaper,
المتعلقة بادارة تلك الصحيفة
especially in such times of conflict?
خاصة في اوقات عصيبة مثل اوقات الصراع الحالي ؟
NA: Well, let me first warn you
نادية السقاف : حسناً .. دعوني اولا احذركم
that I'm not the traditional Yemeni girl.
انني لست الفتاة اليمنية التقليدية
I've guessed you've already noticed this by now.
اعتقد انكم تنبهتم لهذا على الفور
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In Yemen, most women are veiled
في اليمن .. معظم النسوة " منقبات "
and they are sitting behind doors
ويجلسون خلف الابواب المغلقة
and not very much part of the public life.
وليسوا جزء كبير من الحياة العامة
But there's so much potential.
ولكن توجد فرص او آمال كبيرة تعول عليهن
I wish I could show you my Yemen.
لكم أتمنى أن أريكم اليمن خاصتي ..
I wish you could see
اتمنى ان تستطيعوا ان تروا
Yemen through my eyes.
اليمن كما أراها .. من زاويتي
Then you would know
لكي تستطيعوا ان تعلموا
that there's so much to it.
ان هناك الكثير مما لا ترونه حقاً في اليمن
And I was privileged because I was born into a family,
لقد كنت محظوظة في انني ولدت ضمن عائلة
my father would always encourage the boys and the girls.
مميزة تقدر وتشجع الفرص للذكور والاناث على نحو سواء
He would say we are equal.
انه ينظر الينا كأشخاص متساوون
And he was such an extraordinary man.
ان والدي شخص مميز حقاً
And even my mother -- I owe it to my family.
وكذلك والدتي - انا مدينة لعائلتي من اجل ذلك -
A story:
إليكم قصتي
I studied in India.
لقد درست في الهند
And in my third year, I started becoming confused
وفي سنتي الثالثة بدأت أشعر بالارتباك
because I was Yemeni,
لانني يمنية
but I was also mixing up
ولكني اختلط
with a lot of my friends in college.
مع الكثير من الاصدقاء في الجامعة
And I went back home and I said,
وعندما عدت الى منزلي
"Daddy, I don't know who I am.
سألت والدي " والدي .. انا لا أعرف من أنا ..
I'm not a Yemeni; I'm not an Indian."
انا لست يمنية .. ولست هندية "
And he said, "You are the bridge."
فأجابني .. " أنت الجسر/الصلة بين الاثنين "
And that is something I will keep in my heart forever.
وهذا شيء جعلته شعار لي طيلة حياتي وحملته في قلبي
So since then I've been the bridge,
ومذ ذاك الحين غدوت الجسر
and a lot of people have walked over me.
واستغلني الكثير من الاشخاص للعبور الى مكان أفضل ..
PM: I don't think so. (Laughter)
بات ميتشيل : لا أعتقد ذلك ..
NA: But it just helps tell
نادية السقاف : من المفيد ان اقول
that some people are change agents
ان بعض الاشخاص يمثلون عوامل تغيير
in the society.
في المجتمع
And when I became editor-in-chief
لقد غدوت رئيسة تحرير الصحيفة
after my brother actually --
من بعد أخي
my father passed away in 1999,
بعد ان توفي والدي عام 1999
and then my brother until 2005 --
استلم أخي حتى عام 2005
and everybody was betting that I will not be able to do it.
وكان الجميع يهمهم .. أنني لن استطيع إدارة الصحيفة
"What's this young girl coming in and showing off
وقال البعض " مالذي تفعله هذه الفتاة هنا .. كيف تأتي هكذا لتدير المكان ..
because it's her family business," or something.
أهذا فحسب لان الصحيفة مملوكة لعائلتها " وكلام من هذا القبيل
It was very hard at first.
لقد كان الامر صعباُ في البداية
I didn't want to clash with people.
ولم اكن اريد ان احتك كثيراً مع الاخرين
But with all due respect
ولكن مع كامل الاحترام
to all the men, and the older men especially,
للرجال .. وخاصة كبار السن ..
they did not want me around.
معظمهم لم يكن يريدني في الصحيفة
It was very hard, you know,
لقد كان الامر صعباً للغاية
to impose my authority.
خاصة حين فرض السلطة
But a woman's got to do what a woman's got to do.
ولكن على المرأة القيام بما على المرأة القيام به
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And in the first year,
وفي السنة الاولى
I had to fire half of the men.
كنت قد طردت نصف الرجال
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Brought in more women.
واحضرت إناث أكثر
Brought in younger men.
وشباب يافعين أكثر
And we have a more gender-balanced newsroom today.
وقد اصبحت الصحيفة متزنة من حيث توزيع الوظائف لكلا الجنسين ( الذكور والاناث )
The other thing is that it's about professionalism.
والامر الآخر المتعلق بالعمل
It's about proving who you are and what you can do.
انه يجب على المرء ان يثبت نفسه .. وما يمكنه القيام به
And I don't know if I'm going to be boasting now,
ولم اكن أنوي التبجح بإنجازاتنا
but in 2006 alone,
ولكن في عام 2006 وحده
we won three international awards.
ربحنا 3 جوائز عالمية
One of them is the IPI
كانت احداها جائزة مؤسسة الصحافة العالمية
Free Media Pioneer Award.
وجائزة الاعلام الحر " بونيير "
So that was the answer
وكانت هذه الاجابة
to all the Yemeni people.
للشعب اليمني
And I want to score a point here,
وأريد أن أنوه لنقطة هنا
because my husband is in the room over there.
لان زوجي موجود في الغرفة هناك ..
If you could please stand up, [unclear].
هلا قمت من فضلك ..
He has been very supportive of me.
لقد كان من أهم الداعمين لي ..
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
PM: And we should point out
بات ميتشيل : علينا أن ننوه
that he works with you as well at the paper.
انه يعمل معك في ذات الصحيفة
But in assuming this responsibility
الآن ومع الاخذ بعين الاعتبار مسؤوليتك
and going about it as you have,
ومايتوجب عليكي القيام به
you have become a bridge
لكي تكوني جسراً
between an older and traditional society
بين التقاليد الاجتماعية القديمة
and the one that you are now creating at the paper.
وبين تلك التقاليد الجديدة التي تقودينها في الصحيفة
And so along with changing who worked there,
والتي تضمنت تغيير كادر العمل
you must have come up against another positioning
عليكي أيضاً ان تحاربي على جبهة اخرى ..
that we always run into, in particular with women,
متعلقة بالنساء بشكل خاص
and it has to do with outside image,
وبصورتهم التي يأخذها الغرب عنهن
dress, the veiled woman.
المتعلقة بالملبس .. والحجاب
So how have you dealt with this
فكيف تعاملتي مع هذه القضية
on a personal level
على المستوى الشخصي
as well as the women who worked for you?
وعلى مستوى النسوة اللاتي يعملن معك في الصحيفة ؟
NA: As you know,
نادية السقاف : حسناً .. كما تعلمين
the image of a lot of Yemeni women is a lot of black
ان الفكرة التي يأخذها العالم عن اليمنيات .. انهن يلتحفن بالسواد
and covered, veiled women.
وانهن منقبات و مغطيات.
And this is true.
وهذا صحيح
And a lot of it is
ومعظم اسباب هذا
because women are not able, are not free,
ان النساء غير قادرات .. بل لسن يتمتعن بالحرية
to show their face to their self.
في ان يظهرن وجوههن
It's a lot of traditional imposing
ان هذا يحمل على التقاليد الاجتماعية
coming by authority figures
ومصدره رموز الحكم والعرف
such as the men, the grandparents and so on.
مثل الرجال و الاجداد
And it's economic empowerment
وبالانخراط في العمل
and the ability for a woman to say,
سوف يعاد للمرأة قدرتها على التعبير
"I am as much contributing to this family, or more,
وقولها " انا اضيف واساهم في بناء هذه الاسرة .. مثلك ..
than you are."
وربما اكثر - تجاه الزوج - "
And the more empowered the women become,
وكلما قويت شوكة النساء
the more they are able to remove the veil, for example,
كلما كنا قادرات على رفع النقاب، على سبيل المثال ..
or to drive their own car
أو سيستطعن ان يقدن السيارات
or to have a job or to be able to travel.
وان يسافرن .. وان يعملن
So the other face of Yemen
إذاً الوجه الآخر لليمن
is actually one
هو حقيقة
that lies behind the veil,
ذلك الذي يقبع خلف النقاب
and it's economic empowerment mostly
وفقط التطور والتقدم الاقتصادي والانخراط في مجال العمل
that allows the woman to just uncover it.
هو الذي سوف يخول المرأة من عدم إخفاء وجهها
And I have done this throughout my work.
وقد شرعت بنشر هذه الفكرة في عملي ..
I've tried to encourage young girls.
فكنت احاول ان احفز الشابات الصغار
We started with, you can take it off in the office.
وقد بدأت بأن اقول لهن .. بانهن يستطعن ان ينزعن النقاب في المكتب ..
And then after that, you can take it off on assignments.
ومن ثم في المهمات
Because I didn't believe a journalist can be a journalist with --
لانه لا يمكن ان تكون صحفية ..
how can you talk to people if you have your face covered? --
وان تتحدثين مع الناس وانت تضعين النقاب
and so on; it's just a movement.
وعلى هذا .. بدأت هذه الحركة ..
And I am a role model in Yemen.
وقد أصبحت مثال يحتذى به في اليمن
A lot of people look up to me.
والكثير من الناس يتطلعون إلي
A lot of young girls look up to me.
والكثير من الفتيات يتطلعن إلي
And I need to prove to them that, yes, you can still be married,
وانا احتاج ان اثبت لهن .. انه يمكن للمرأة ان تكون متزوجة
you can still be a mother,
وان تكون والدة
and you can still be respected within the society,
وان تكون محترمة في مجتمعها
but at the same time,
وفي نفس الوقت
that doesn't mean you [should] just be one of the crowd.
لا يعني هذا انه عليك ان تكوني فرد في القطيع
You can be yourself and have your face.
بل عليكي ان تكوني نفسك .. وان تثبتي وجودك
PM: But by putting yourself personally out there --
بات ميتشيل : بكون تحركاتك بصورة شخصية في المجتمع
both projecting a different image
وببث صورة مغايرة
of Yemeni women,
عن النساء اليمنيات
but also what you have made possible
واعتقد ان هذا يمكن ان ينسحب على النساء
for the women who work at the paper --
الذين يعملن معك في الصحيفة ايضاً
has this put you in personal danger?
هل تعرضن أنفسكن للخطر جراء هذا ؟
NA: Well the Yemen Times, across 20 years,
نادية السقاف : صحيفة " اليمن تايمز " على مدى 20 عام
has been through so much.
تعرضت لعدة انواع من الضغوط
We've suffered prosecution;
لقد قاضونا كثيراً
the paper was closed down more than three times.
ولقد اغلقت الصحيفة اكثر من 3 مرات
It's an independent newspaper,
نحن صحيفة مستقلة
but tell that to the people in charge.
ولكن لا يعي المسؤولون هذا
They think that if there's anything against them,
هم يعتقدون انه ما ان ننشر شيئاً ضدهم ..
then we are being an opposition newspaper.
فاننا صحيفة معارضة لهم ولسنا مستقلين
And very, very difficult times.
انه امر صعب للغاية
Some of my reporters were arrested.
بعض الصحفين العاملين في الصحيفة ألقي القبض عليهم
We had some court cases.
ناهيكم عن الدعاوي الكثيرة
My father was assassinated.
واغتيال والدي
Today, we are in a much better situation.
اليوم .. نحن في وضع افضل
We've created the credibility.
لقد صنعنا مصداقيتنا
And in times of revolution or change like today,
وفي اوقات مثل هذه الاوقات التي تمر فيها اليمن من الثورة والتغير
it is very important for independent media to have a voice.
من المهم جداً ان يكون للاعلام المستقل صوت
It's very important
انه مهم جداً
for you to go to YemenTimes.com,
تتطلعوا على اخبارنا على موقع YemenTimes.com
and it's very important
من الضروري جداً
to listen to our voice.
ان يستمع الناس لصوتنا
And this is probably something
وهذا شيء أريد ..
I'm going to share with you
ان اشارككم فيه
in Western media probably --
في الاعلام الغربي عادة
and how there's a lot of stereotypes --
هناك الكثير من الاحكام المسبقة
thinking of Yemen in one single frame:
والتي تضع اليمن في اطار واحد
this is what Yemen is all about.
وتصور اليمن ضمن ذلك الاطار فحسب
And that's not fair.
وهذا ظلم ..
It's not fair for me; it's not fair for my country.
ظلم لي كشخص .. ظلم لوطني ..
A lot of reporters come to Yemen
العديد من المراسلين يأتون الى اليمن
and they want to write a story on Al-Qaeda or terrorism.
وهم لا يريدون سوى كتابة مقالة عن تنظيم القاعدة او الارهاب
And I just wanted to share with you:
واريد ان اخطركم بشيء ..
there's one reporter that came.
هناك مراسل قدم الى اليمن
He wanted to do a documentary
وكان يريد ان يصور فلم وثائقي
on what his editors wanted.
بحسب توجيهات محرريه ..
And he ended up writing about a story that even surprised me --
ولكنه انتهى بتصوير قصة فاجئتني تماما
hip hop --
عن الهيب هوب !
that there are young Yemeni men
التي يستخدمها اليمنيون الشباب
who express themselves
في التعبير عن انفسهم
through dancing and puchu puchu.
عن طريق الرقص و الاصوات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That thing. (PM: Rap. Break dancing.)
بهذا الاسلوب (بات ميتشيل : تقصدين الراب .. والرقص الأرضي )
Yeah, break dancing.
نعم " البريك دانس - الرقص الارضي "
I'm not so old.
لست كبيرة السن الى هذا الحد ..
I'm just not in touch.
كل ما في الامر أنني لست على اطلاع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
PM: Yes, you are.
بات ميتشيل : نعم أنت كذلك ..
Actually, that's a documentary
في الواقع هذا الفلم الوثائقي .
that's available online; the video's online.
موجود على الانترنت
NA: ShaketheDust.org.
نادية السقاف : على موقع ShaketheDust.org
PM: "Shake the Dust." (NA: "Shake the Dust.")
بات ميتشيل :" أزيحوا الغبار " (نادية السقاف : نعم ازيحوا الغبار )
PM: ShaketheDust.org.
بات ميتشيل :ShaketheDust.org
And it definitely does give a different image of Yemen.
سوف يعطيكم حتماً .. هذا صورة مغايرة عن اليمن
You spoke about the responsibility of the press.
لقد تحدثتي عن مسؤولية الاعلام
And certainly, when we look
لكن حتماً عندما ننظر
at the ways in which we have separated ourselves from others
الى الطرق التي يعتمدها البعض بعزل أنفسهم عن الآخرين
and we've created fear
فنحن نصنع الخوف
and danger,
والخطر
often from lack of knowledge,
بسبب نقص المعرفة
lack of real understanding,
ونقص الفهم
how do you see
كيف ترين
the way that the Western press in particular
الطريقة التي يتعامل بها الاعلام الغربي على وجه الخصوص
is covering this and all other stories out of the region,
تغطية اخبار المنطقة
but in particular, in your country?
وخاصة في بلدكم اليمن ؟
NA: Well there is a saying that says,
نادية السقاف : هناك قول مأثور يقول
"You fear what you don't know,
" أنت تخاف ما تجهله ..
and you hate what you fear."
وانت تكره ما تخافه "
So it's about the lack of research, basically.
ان المشكلة في الاساس هي نقص البحث والاطلاع
It's almost, "Do your homework," --
يمكنني ان اقول انه " تقصير في اداء الواجب "
some involvement.
وفي الاندامج في المجتمع قبل اعداد القصة
And you cannot do parachute reporting --
انت لا تستطيع ان تغطي او تعد تقرير
just jump into a country for two days
عن دولة ما بالذهاب اليها ليومين
and think that you've done your homework and a story.
وتعد قصتك وتعود وتظن انك قمت بعملك
So I wish
انا اتمنى ان يتعرف
that the world would know my Yemen,
العالم على اليمن الذي اعرفه انا
my country, my people.
بلدي انا ..اهلي انا .. شعبي انا
I am an example, and there are others like me.
انا مثال عن اهل اليمن .. وهناك كثير من الاشخاص مثلي
We may not be that many,
ربما لسنا كثرة ..
but if we are promoted
ولكن وان تم تسليط الضوء علينا
as a good, positive example,
كمثال جيد للفرد .. ومثال ايجابي
there will be others -- men and women --
سوف يكون هناك المزيد .. من الرجال والنساء
who can eventually bridge the gap --
والذي يستطيعون ان يردموا من الهوة التي تفصل بيننا
again, coming to the bridge --
ومرة اخرى .. اعود الى الجسر ..
between Yemen and the world
اقصد الجسر بين اليمن والعالم
and telling first
فمن المهم بداية
about recognition
الاعتراف بوجود الاشخاص
and then about communication
ومن ثم التواصل معهم
and compassion.
من ثم التعاطف
I think Yemen is going to be
واعتقد ان اليمن
in a very bad situation
سوف يمر الان بظروف سيئة جداً
in the next two or three years.
في العامين او الثلاث القادمة
It's natural.
وهذا امر طبيعي
But after the two years, which is a price we are willing to pay,
ولكن بعد العامين .. واللذان هما الثمن الذي سندفعه لأجل الثورة
we are going to stand up again on our feet,
سوف نقف مرة اخرى على اقدامنا
but in the new Yemen
ولكن في يمن جديد
with a younger and more empowered people --
يمد يده للشباب ويدفعهم للانخراط في العمل فيه
democratic.
في يمن ديموقراطي
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
PM: Nadia, I think you've just given us
بات ميتشيل : نادية .. اعتقد انك اعطيتني
a very different view of Yemen.
صورة اخرى عن اليمن
And certainly you yourself and what you do
وانا متاكدة انك وعملك
have given us a view of the future
لقد اعطيتمونا صورة مستقبلية عن اليمن
that we will embrace
نقدرها
and be grateful for.
ونمتن لها
And the very best of luck to you.
واتمنى لك كامل الحظ والتوفيق لك ولموقعكم
YemenTimes.com.
YemenTimes.com.
NA: On Twitter also.
نادية السقاف : وعلى موقع تويتر أيضاً
PM: So you are plugged in.
بات ميتشيل : أنت موجودة إذاً على كل نواح الانترنت
(Applause)
(تصفيق)